Finding Aid for Warren S. Wilkinson papers, 1801-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren S. Wilkinson papers 1801-1991
Wilkinson, Warren S.
93840 Aa 2
Scrapbooks of Warren S. Wilkinson, member of the board of the Evening News Association, publisher of the Detroit News. Scrapbooks relate to the life and work of James E. Scripps, founder of the Detroit News, and to the struggle over the sale of the newspaper to Gannett Company in 1985.
1 linear feet in 3 boxes
5 oversize volumes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren W. Wilkinson (donor no. 8155 ) donated 5 scrapbooks to the Bentley Historical Library in 1993. In 2009 additional scrapbooks were loaned to the library for copying.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Warren Scripps Wilkinson was born in 1920, son of Almadus DeGrasse Wilkinson and Harriet Gertrude Whitcomb Wilkinson. Through his mother's family, Wilkinson is a descendant of James E. Scripps, founder of the Detroit News. Wilkinson was a member of the board of directors of the Evening News Association, owner of the Detroit News along with other newspapers and broadcasting stations.
The collection contains scrapbooks assembled by Wilkinson relating to the life and work of James E. Scripps, as well as the machinations surrounding the sale of the Evening News Association to Gannett Company in 1985. Most of the scrapbooks have been copied for the library and the originals returned to the donor. The collection consists of photocopies of the scrapbooks along with scanned images of many of the photographs. Scanned photos are identified by the scan number noted on the reverse of the page.
The family scrapbooks document James E. Scripps's personal life and his family, the history of the Detroit News, Scripps family interests including the Detroit Museum of Art, the Scripps home on Trumbull Avenue in Detroit, and Trinity Episcopal Church located at the corner of Trumbull and Grand River Avenues in Detroit one block from the family home.
Wilkinson's scrapbooks titled "The Twilight of the Evening News Association" contain photos, correspondence, trial transcripts, financial charts, and commentary documenting the company's struggle for profitability in the 1960s and 70s, and negotiations and lawsuits over the sale of the company in the 1980s. The first volume in this sequence contains many photos of News operations from the early part of the twentieth century.
Subjects:
Scripps family.; Scripps, James E. (James Edmund), 1835-1906.; Detroit Museum of Art.; Evening News Association.; Trinity Church (Detroit, Mich.); Woodmere Cemetery (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit news.; American newspapers--Michigan--Detroit.; Anglican church buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Art museums--Michigan--Detroit.; Cemeteries--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Scripps family.; Scripps, James E. (James Edmund), 1835-1906.; Detroit Museum of Art.; Evening News Association.; Trinity Church (Detroit, Mich.); Woodmere Cemetery (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit news.; Episcopal churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Galleries and museums--Michigan--Detroit.; Mansions--Michigan--Detroit.; Newspaper editors--Michigan--Detroit.; Newspaper industry--Michigan--Detroit.; Newsrooms--Michigan--Detroit.; Reporters--Michigan--Detroit.; Tombs and sepulchral monuments--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- James E. Scripps, personal scrapbooks
  - Volume 1. The Scripps's in England; John Mogg Scripps and Rushville, Illinois; The family of Harriet Messinger, James Scripps's wife; James Scripps personal life in Chicago and Detroit 1859-1869, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 2. James Scripps's personal life 1870-1891, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 3. James Scripps's personal life 1892-1901, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 4. James Scripps's personal life 1902-1906; Non-newspaper businesses in which James Scripps was involved, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 5. Dramatis personae--Elizabeth, James, and Ellen, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 6A. Dramatis personae--William A., George H., Julia Anne, Frederick Tudor, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 7. Art and architecture--Detroit Museum of Art, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 8. Art and architecture--Detroit Museum of Art and Scripps home, photocopies (Box 1)
  - Volume 8A. Art and architecture--Trinity Church and Woodmere Cemetery, photocopies (Box 1)
- The Twilight of the Evening News Association 1967-1985 A Morality Story
  - Introduction and chronology, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Cast of characters, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Stockholder relations, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Operations, photocopies (Box 2)
  - The struggle for control, photocopies (Box 2)
  - The issue of a joint operating agreement with the Free Press, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Notes on the Smith-Hague litigation, photocopies (Box 2)
  - The great stockholder revolt, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Peter Kizer and the Lear-Perenchio tender offer, photocopies (Box 2)
  - The tender offer litigation, photocopies (Box 2)
  - The final battle, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Untitled section, photocopies (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous files
  - James E. Scripps manuscript 1905, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Scripps newspaper expansions 1878-1887, photocopies (Box 2)
  - Whitcomb family scrapbook 1A, photocopies (Box 2)
  - List of photos scanned by Bentley Historical Library, photocopies (Box 2)
- The Twilight of the Evening News Association scrapbooks
  - Volume 1 [includes photographs of the Evening News, 1906-1960s, photocopies (Box 3)
  - Volume 2, originals (Volume 1)
  - Volume 3, originals (Volume 2)
  - Volume 4, originals (Volume 3)
  - Volume 5, originals (Volume 4)
  - Volume 6, originals (Volume 5)
- James E. Scripps, the publisher scrapbooks
  - Volume 1. James E. Scripps, the publisher 1857-1885, photocopies (Box 3)
  - Volume 2. James E. Scripps, the publisher 1886-1898, photocopies (Box 3)
  - Volume 3. James E. Scripps, the publisher 1899-1906, photocopies (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous scrapbook
  - Scripps miscellaneous (Box 3)